Today's דף *Daf* is ל"א lo, *Lamed Aleph*, and we pick up
at the very bottom of ל' עמוד ב' *Lamed Amud Bet*, and
we're dealing with two explanations about why a normal person would go
to the מקוה mikvah, *Mikvah* before entering into the בית המקדש Beit
HaMikdash, *Beit HaMikdash*. One is learned out from the כהן גדול Kohen
Gadol, *Kohen Gadol*, more sort of a ritual preparation for entering into
the space; the other is a סרך טבילה tevilah *Serach Tvilah* to
remember that you might be טמא tamei *Tamei*. As I pointed out,
that might be parallel to the explanations of why the כהן גדול
Kohen Gadol *Kohen Gadol* has a seven-day wait. And now the גמרא
Gemara *Gemara* says like this. אמר ליה אביי לרב יוסף *Amar lei
Abaye l'Rav Yosef*, Abaye says to Rav Yosef, very last line of
ל' עמוד ב' *Lamed Amud Bet*, very last line of ל' עמוד
ב' *Lamed Amud Bet*. אמר ליה אביי לרב יוסף *Amar lei Abaye
l'Rav Yosef*, Abaye says to Rav Yosef: so some say רבי יהודה
Rabbi Yehuda. דאמר סרך טבילה tevilah, זו *Rabbi Yehuda d'amar Serach Tvilah
zu*, or some just say it's a general question: טבילה tevilah. זו
חוצצת או אינה חוצצת *Tvilah zu chotzetset o einah chotzetset*? This טבילה
tevilah, *Tvilah*, according especially according to רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda. *Rabbi Yehuda*
that says it's only to remind you that you might be טמא
tamei *Tamei*, how much are we going to apply the normal laws
of טבילה tevilah. *Tvilah*? How much are we going to say that
you can't do it if you have a חציצה *Chatzitzah*? So meaning
it's not really to make you טהור tahor *Tahor*, it's not really
doesn't accomplish anything, it's just a reminder. So אמר ליה *Amar lei*,
so exactly. So he said back to him: כל דתקון רבנן Rabbanan
כעין דאורייתא תקון *Kol d'tikun rabanan k'ein d'oraita tikun*. Anything the Rabbis
did, they established, they established that it should be just like the
biblical model. And here, in addition to the fact like yes, you
know, if you're going to do it, do it right and, you
know, have it be something of weight and significance, I would also
say that if it's supposed to remind you that you might be
טמא tamei *Tamei*, the more you have to go through the procedure
and you're treating it as a real טבילה tevilah. *Tvilah* of becoming
טהור tahor *Tahor*, the more it's going to serve that function. Okay.
Now אמר ליה אביי לרב יוסף *Amar lei Abaye l'Rav Yosef*, so
Abaye said to Rav Yosef: ביאה במקצת שמה ביאה או לא *Biah
b'miktzat shema biah o lo*? If a person only partially enters into
the בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash, *Beit HaMikdash*, is that considered entering in
or not? Now that's a general question even by somebody that is
really טמא tamei, *Tamei*, right? A person who is really טמא *Tamei*
who enters into the בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash. *Beit HaMikdash* is like,
you know, חייב מיתה chayav misah. בידי שמים *Chayav mitah b'yedei shamayim*,
and what happens if you only partially enter in? So some people,
for example, are very careful not to put the קוויטלאך *Kvitlach*, the
in the in the niches of the כותל *Kotel*, not just because
of the sort of superstitious aspects of related to that from a
rationalistic perspective, but because well because if you say that the הר
הבית Har HaBayit. *Har HaBayit* begins at the כותל *Kotel*, the כותל
*Kotel* surrounds the הר הבית *Har HaBayit*, you all know that right,
not not the actual מקדש Mikdash. *Mikdash*, okay, and if you say
it begins at the outer edge of the wall, not at the
inner edge of the wall, then when you're sticking in your finger,
you're sticking part of your body into the zone of the הר
הבית *Har HaBayit*. Now okay, is that a problem if you have
a certain type of טומאה tumah *Tumah*? If you're a בעל קרי
*Baal Keri*, if you're a נדה niddah *Niddah*, טומאה tumah היוצאה מגופו
*Tumah Hayotzei Migufo*. So that would be an example about ביאה במקצת
*Biah B'miktzat*. Now here the issue is that the מצורע metzora, *Metzora*
sticks his thumbs
into the עזרה azarah *Azarah*, so he is actually a מחוסר כיפורים
*Mechusar Kippurim*, you know, he lacks the קרבן korban *Korban*, the atonement,
and he's not allowed to go into the עזרה azarah? *Azarah*, but
he's sticking his thumbs into the עזרה azarah *Azarah*. Now that actually
we know is allowed because there's sort of like no alternative; that's
how the תורה Torah *Torah* process is done. But here the question
is relating to so that's like a general question about ביאה במקצת
*Biah B'miktzat* when somebody is טמא *Tamei*. But here the question relates
to this requirement, this new requirement of everybody to go to the
מקוה mikvah *Mikvah* before. Okay, so if I if the הלכה halacha:
*Halacha* is there's a new הלכה halakhah *Halacha*, maybe it's Rabbinic, maybe
it's based on the פסוק pasuk *Pasuk* by the כהן גדול Kohen
Gadol. *Kohen Gadol*, anybody before entering the עזרה azarah? *Azarah* has to
go into the has to go to the מקוה mikvah. *Mikvah*. What
if I only want to stick my finger into the עזרה azarah,
*Azarah*? Do I still have to go to the מקוה mikvah *Mikvah*
or not? What הלכה *Halacha* would we apply for that requirement of
going to the מקוה mikvah *Mikvah* before if my entering is only
ביאה במקצת *Biah B'miktzat*? Okay, so that's the question. ביאה במקצת שמה
ביאה או לא *Biah b'miktzat shema biah o lo*? אמר ליה *Amar
lei*, so he back to him: בהנך יוכיחו *Be-hanch yoichi'u*. Again the
same answer about the מצורע metzora *Metzora*. The his thumbs will be
a proof שהן ביאה במקצת *shehen biah b'miktzat*. He's only going to
enter put his thumbs in, ותניא Vetanya. מצורע metzora טובל tovel, ועומד
בשער ניקנור *V'tanya Metzora tovel v'omed b'Shaar Nikanor*. And we have taught
that the מצורע metzora, *Metzora* has to go to the מקוה mikvah
*Mikvah* before entering in, and the only reason that רבי יהודה *Rabbi
Yehuda* disagrees if you'll remember is because he went to the מקוה
mikvah. *Mikvah* the day before. But everybody agrees that fundamentally the מצורע
metzora. *Metzora* is required to do this טבילה tevilah, *Tvilah* before entering,
even though he's not really fully entering, he's just sticking his thumbs
in. Okay, so that's your answer to that, which is a little
ironic then that in order to put his thumbs in he has
to go to the מקוה mikvah. *Mikvah*, but for the real laws
of טומאה וטהרה tumah vetaharah, *Tumah v'Tahara*, because he's really a מחוסר
כיפורים *Mechusar Kippurim*, he's still allowed to stick his thumbs into the
עזרה azarah, *Azarah* even though he is not allowed to himself enter
because he lacks the final קרבן korban *Korban*. Okay, so we can't
do anything about that; that's the process of טהרה *Tahara*. But for
this requirement of מקוה mikvah. *Mikvah*, that we're going to demand even
if he's only sticking his thumbs in. איבעיא להו *Ibaia lehu*. Now
they raised the following question: מהו שיעשה סכין ארוכה וישחוט *Mahu she-yaaseh
sakin aruchah v'yishchot*? Okay, now we have... But again, the same type
of questions we can ask about somebody who is טמא: can he
stick his thumbs in? Can a טמא person stand outside the עזרה
azarah. and שחט shecht with a knife a קרבן korban in the
עזרה? azarah. Because we learn out that the קרבן has to be
לפני ה', lifnei Hashem, but the שוחט shochet doesn't have to be
לפני ה'. lifnei Hashem. Okay, so can a, so the גמרא Gemara
elsewhere asks the question: so can a טמא person stand outside the
עזרה Azarah. with a long knife and שחט shecht a קרבן in
the עזרה?
Azarah I mean, assume that's technically possible, might not be,
because you lose a lot of control and okay, whatever. I understand
this is a theoretical, really like very clarifying. Right. But practical, I
don't think so.
Okay. All right, so we'll keep it at the theoretical. So this
is the question. So it was a question about a טמא person.
But here the question is, that's normally how the question's asked, here
the question is asked about a טהור tahor, person who didn't go
to the מקוה, mikvah: right? So we have this new requirement that
any טהור person, even if you're טהור, you go to the מקוה
mikvah before entering into the מקדש. Mikdash, And so there's two ways
of interesting testing the limit of this. I'm not really entering the
מקדש, Mikdash. just my thumbs are entering the מקדש. Mikdash Sorry, you
still have to go to the מקוה. mikvah? I'm not entering the
מקדש Mikdash at all, I'm just doing an עבודה avodah in the
מקדש Mikdash. without entering in. I'm doing a long-distance עבודה, avodah, but
I personally am not going in the מקדש. Mikdash, Okay, what's the
story? Now you remember by the way that תוספות Tosafot said if
we learn it from the כהן גדול, Kohen Gadol, that the actual
model of the כהן גדול Kohen Gadol. is not just entering the
מקדש, Mikdash. it's entering to do the עבודה. avodah. That's the actual
model of the כהן גדול. Kohen Gadol, We split off one piece
of that and said that even if you just enter, you have
to go. In a way, this is the other piece: you're just
doing an עבודה avodah without entering, do you have to go? So
let's see what the גמרא Gemara answers. Okay,
איבעיא להו לבן זומא, איבעיא להו לרבנן. I-ba-ya le-hu le-Ben Zoma, i-ba-ya
le-hu le-Rabbanan. You could ask this either according to בן זומא Ben
Zoma that says the reason is you learn from a כהן גדול,
Kohen Gadol and איבעיא להו לרבנן דפליגי עליה דרבי יהודה, i-ba-ya le-hu
le-Rabbanan di-pligi alei de-Rabbi Yehuda, and you could ask the rabbis who
argue on רבי יהודה. Remember the rabbis who said that even in
a מצורע, that normal people, only a מצורע has to go, normal
people don't have to go? So that was a position that they
completely reject the idea of going to the מקוה mikvah, before entering
into the מקדש. Mikdash So let's see how it works out either
way. איבעיא להו לבן זומא, I-ba-ya le-hu le-Ben Zoma, you could ask
according to בן זומא Ben Zoma that says that everybody has to
go to the מקוה mikvah, before entering. עד כאן לא מחייב בן
זומא, Ad kan lo mechayev Ben Zoma, until now בן זומא Ben
Zoma only demands going to the מקוה mikvah אלא לגוואי, ela le-gavai,
if you're actually entering inward. אבל לבראי, Aval le-barai, if you're on
the outside, לא, you would say no. The requirement is when you
enter, not when you don't enter. End of story. או דלמא, O
dilma, or maybe you say the opposite: אתי לאמשוכי, Ati le-imshuchi, that
if you're already doing the עבודה avodah and you're שוחט, shochet, as
Dov says, it's very hard to manage that and you'll come to,
you know, be drawn after the act that you're doing and you'll
come to overstep the line. So it's interesting the גמרא Gemara frames
it as a חשש, chashash, as a concern you might overstep the
line, right? Because I could have said as I said, as I
was saying before, it could be a formal idea, right? עבודה Avodah
itself might demand טבילה tevilah the same way entering demands טבילה, tevilah,
maybe עבודה avodah demands טבילה. tevilah But the גמרא Gemara, has it
as a חשש, chashash, as a concern: technically you shouldn't have to,
but we're afraid you might come to overstep the line. That's according
to בן זומא. Ben Zoma. איבעיא להו לרבנן דפליגי עליה דרבי יהודה,
I-ba-ya le-hu le-Rabbanan di-pligi alei de-Rabbi Yehuda, now you can ask according
to the rabbis that argue on רבי יהודה. The rabbis who say
that only a מצורע does the טבילה, no a normal person does
not do the טבילה. Normally they don't require it. So now you
could say עד כאן לא קאמרי רבנן התם. ad kan lo ka-amri
Rabbanan hatam. Until now the rabbis say a normal person who goes
into the מקדש Mikdash, doesn't have to go to the מקוה. mikvah,
דלא קא עביד עבודה, De-lo ka avid avodah, you're not coming to
do an עבודה. avodah. אבל הכא דקא עביד עבודה, Aval hacha de-ka
avid avodah, here you're doing an עבודה, avodah, so מודו modu maybe
they would disagree, maybe they'd say yeah, anybody who is doing an
עבודה, avodah, that we admit requires a טבילה. או דלמא לא שנא,
O dilma lo shena, or maybe it doesn't matter. תיקו, Teiku, and
that remains as an unanswered question. So from here we have two
different reasons about why a normal person is required to go to
the מקוה. mikvah. And by the way, there's also the opinion of
the רבנן Rabbanan, that reject it and say a normal person does
not go to the מקוה. mikvah, But two different reasons why a
person would go to the מקוה: mikvah one is to remind him
he might be טמא, the other is a ritual before entering into
the space, as I said nicely parallels the seven days of the
כהן גדול. Kohen Gadol According to one, it's a concern of טומאה
tumah with the ashes of the פרה אדומה Parah Adumah and the
whole thing. And according to the two main reasons in the beginning
of the גמרא, Gemara it's more about this ritual of preparation. And
even there we see a nice parallel, because is it a preparation
to enter the space, learn from הר סיני, Har Sinai, remember by
the כהן גדול, Kohen Gadol or is it a preparation to do
the עבודה, avodah, learn from the מלואים? miluim? And here too, right,
the גמרא Gemara focuses on the preparation for entering the space, anybody
who just enters. But as תוספות Tosafot points out, the actual פסוקים
pesukim by the כהן גדול Kohen Gadol. are about entering to do
the עבודה. avodah. And that's the question the גמרא Gemara. revisits here:
let's say you're just doing the עבודה avodah without entering the space.
So very nice parallel to the reasons of the כהן גדול Kohen
Gadol is a normal person who enters
must go into the מקוה mikvah? before entering or doing an עבודה.
avodah. Yes.
I have a bit of a related question.
Yes, go for it.
Is it אסור assur to have relations if the woman is טמאה
temeiah and needs to go to the
מקוה? mikvah, It's a נדה niddah. specifically. Right. It's a נדה. niddah...
Right. Is the נדה... niddah No.
The only טומאה that translates into an איסור ביאה, issur bi'ah, to
a prohibition against sex, is the טומאה of a נדה niddah or
זבה. zavah. Nothing that relates to a man and no other טומאות
tumot that relate to a woman. Now, it is true that by
a מצורע, חז״ל Chazal understand בדד ישב, badad yeshev, he must be
alone, which means that he must be outside of his house, he
can't have sex with his wife, but that's of a different nature.
And also interestingly that does not apply by a woman who's a
מצורע. So she's...
but fundamentally it only applies to a נדה and a זב. zav.
Okay. Alright, let's take a look back at the גמרא. Gemara חמש
טבילות ועשרה קידושין טובל. Chamesh tevilot ve'asarah kiddushin tovel. Now we get
finally, finally, not like we're not going to pull back out again—we
keep on sort of zooming out and zooming in—but now we're going
to zoom in again into the כהן גדול Kohen Gadol about the
חמש טבילות chamesh tevilot he would do and the ten washings of
hands, one before and after each טבילה, we'll see details about that
later, on יום כיפור. Yom Kippur. Okay, and the first one he
did before entering into the עזרה, Azarah to the בית המקדש, Beit
HaMikdash, taking off his weekday garments, putting on his כהונה kehunah garments,
and as we've seen that was a normal טבילה that normal people
would do anyway.
Okay, so תנו רבנן, Tanu Rabbanan, our Rabbis taught: חמש טבילות ועשרה
קידושין טובל כהן גדול ומקדש בו ביום. Chamesh tevilot ve'asarah kiddushin tovel
Kohen Gadol umekadesh bo bayom. He would go ten times to the
מקוה, mikvah. five times to the מקוה, mikvah, ten times washing his
hands. וכולן בקודש בבית הפרוה. Vechulan bekodesh bevet haparvah. They were all
in the עזרה, in the holy space, on the top of this
בית הפרוה, Beit HaParvah, on top of this chamber. חוץ מראשונה שעשה
בחול, Chutz merishonah she'asah bechol, except for the first one that he
did in a non-sanctified space, because you have to go to the
מקוה mikvah, before entering into the sanctified space. על גבי שער המים,
Al gabi Sha'ar HaMayim, by the, on top of the gate of
water. ובצד לשכתו היתה. Uvetzad lishkato hayitah. And that was next to
his chamber where he has been staying that week. Okay, if we
remember there was a whole question about where his chamber was, and
was his chamber opened to קודש, kodesh, opened into חול? chol? He's
sleeping in his chamber, presumably his chamber has to be חול chol
either based on the space that it's in or based on the
space that it's open into. And similarly,
this place of the טבילה, and it makes sense that the place
of the טבילה would be close to where he's been staying, so
that would be nearby where he was staying, right on top of
this gate, and that's where he would go and that would be
בחול bechol before he began the עבודה. avodah. Okay. אמר אביי, Amar
Abaye, let me look at the משנה Mishnah for one second.
Was one of the possibilities a chamber inside the width of שער
ניקנור? Sha'ar Nikanor?
There is a chamber like that, but that's not what we're talking
about here, no. Okay. So now it says like this. אמר אביי,
Amar Abaye, שמע מינה, shema mina, we can infer from this point,
שעין עיטם, she'Ein Eitam, the wellspring of עיטם, Eitam, which they understood
was the wellspring from where they drew the water for the מקדש,
and where the water came for the מקוה, mikvah. גבוה מקרקע עזרה
עשרים ושלוש אמות. gavoha mikarka azarah esrim veshalosh amot. It's twenty-three אמות
amot higher than the floor of the עזרה. How do you know
that? דתנן, Detnan, because we learn in the משנה: Mishnah: כל הפתחים
שהיו שם, Kol hapetachim shehayu sham, all of the gates that were
in the בית המקדש, Beis HaMikdash גובהן עשרים אמה. govhan esrim amah.
Is the well in Eitam some place else? A well in a
different mountain and it's feeding the water, yeah, presumably there's a map.
Let me see the map. Jerusalem baths, that's nice. Upper aqueduct, Solomon's
pools. They think the עין עיטם Ein Eitam is down here, past
בית לחם. Beit Lechem. Right. Wow. Eitam spring alongside Solomon's pools. A
long aqueduct flows from this spring for roughly twenty kilometers. Wow. So
they actually have uncovered the aqueduct? Yes. This picture, winding between the
mountains, passing through tunnels until it reaches Temple Mount. The present day
עין עיטם Ein Eitam spring is located at an altitude seven hundred
and sixty meters above sea level, twenty-five meters higher than the Temple
Mount. Of course you need it to be higher in order for
the aqueduct to be gravity-fed. This was destroyed at the time
of the destruction of the Temple but later restored.
Wow, that's pretty amazing. Look at that. Let me see if it's
even further south than בית לחם. Beit Lechem. Yeah, there's pieces of
that aqueduct still existing. Wow. Okay. So great. So this is going
to be the water that feeds the בית המקדש. Beis HaMikdash. And
it has to be and it's going to be twenty-three אמות amot
higher than the עזרה. How do we know it? דתנן. Detnan. כל
הפתחים שהיו שם. Kol hapetachim shehayu sham. All of the gates that
were there. גובהן עשרים אמה. govhan esrim amah. They're twenty אמות amot
tall. ורוחבן עשר אמות. verochban eser amot. And ten אמות amot
wide. חוץ משל אולם. Chutz mishel Ulam. Except for the אולם, Ulam,
which isn't our concern. ותניא. Vetanya: Now, he was on top of
one of the gates. He was on top of the gate of
the שער המים, Sha'ar HaMayim, aptly named. ותניא: ורחץ את בשרו במים
Verachatz et besaro bamayim במי מקוה. bemay mikvah. So now we're going
to learn the basic size of a מקוה. mikveh, So person washes
his flesh with water, this is by the כהן גדול. kohein gadol,
So that means not normal water, but he has to go into
a
מקוה, mikveh כל בשרו. Kol besaro. entire flesh. So here we learn
a הלכה: מים שכל גופו עולה בהם, Mayim shekol gufo oleh bahem,
that the מקווה Mikva has to be the size
that his entire body can be submerged in it. וכמה הן? V'kama
hein? How big is that? אמה על אמה ברום שלוש אמות, Ama
al ama b'rom shalosh amot, an אמה ama by an אמה ama
by three אמות amot high. Now, I want to stop here for
a second because three אמות amot is about four and a half
feet, and even though people in the past were shorter, they weren't
that much shorter, and תוספות Tosafot raises the question. תוספות, Tosafot, based
on other גמרות, Gemarot, also points out that three אמות amot gets
you basically to your shoulder height. It does not get you to
the top of your head. So he raises the question, if three
אמות amot only gets you to your shoulder height, how does an
אמה ama by an אמה ama by three אמות amot get your
entire body to be submerged? So one answer is, right, you crouch.
You crouch, you
bend your knees, but then he's got an even better answer, which
is: if the walls of the מקווה Mikva are higher, the water
displacement takes care of it. So you go in, it starts at
shoulder height, but the water displacement raises the water over your head.
Okay, but even if the walls of the מקווה Mikva aren't high,
yes, you crouch and you bend your knees. So that's why you
have an אמה ama by an אמה ama by three אמות. amot.
Now, שיעור חכמים מי מקווה ארבעים סאה, Shiur chachamim mei mikva arbaim
seah, that would be 40, and that would be
40 סאה. seah. Okay,
which is our size of a מקווה. Mikva. Now, so now, what's
the proof? The proof is like this.
The proof is
that
here's your שער המים, Sha'ar HaMayim, right, and then it's a gate
like that, okay,
and you have your מקווה Mikva built on here, like it usually
goes on top of the שער המים. Sha'ar HaMayim. Okay, for some
reason some space to walk around, I don't know exactly anyway. Okay,
here's the מקווה Mikva right here, this is where the כהן גדול
kohein gadol stays during the week, you know, okay, there's steps that
go up. Okay, that's the מקווה Mikva he goes to, okay, on
top of the שער המים. Sha'ar HaMayim. So the שער המים Sha'ar
HaMayim is 20 אמה, ama, and the מקווה Mikva is one by
one by three. Now תוספות Tosafot asks, how do we know it
was built those parameters? Maybe it was built like a bathtub. But
let's assume that that's the normal way a מקווה Mikva is built.
So the top of the מקווה Mikva is 23 אמות amot off
of the ground, off of the קרקע karka of the עזרה. So
the wellspring that feeds it has to be coming down. Right, so
the wellspring that feeds it has to be higher than 23—than 23
אמה ama off of the floor of the עזרה in order to—is
it anywhere near?
I don't know.
Well, look, here's what they got, this is exactly what—now, I don't
understand something about that aqueduct, and I was going to ask about
this
because, you know, this is a mountain, right? So if this is
a mountain,
somebody explain this to me, I don't get it. Here's הר הבית.
Okay, in order to get something up a mountain, you got to
either—it doesn't matter if your original source is high up here and
you're aiming at בית לחם, Beit Lechem, as opposed to sea level,
you know, what are you going to
do? Where's—how are you going to get it up the mountain? You
have to build like an aqueduct up, you know, Roman aqueduct. It
has to be off the ground, not in the ground. Those pictures
are aqueducts in the ground, right?
But at a certain point
the aqueduct has to be off the ground. Which then raises interesting
questions about שאובין, she'uvin, you know, drawn water.
That's the question I was about to ask.
But, you know, again, there's questions. It might not technically be a
כלי kli if it's made out of metal, not made out of
metal. Is there human agency or does it flow naturally? But this
would raise interesting questions, right? I mean look, when the rainwater comes
down the מקווה, Mikva, right, there are pipes that bring it from
the rooftop to the—so how does that work? So, you know, so
in terms of the laws of שאובין, she'uvin, you know, especially if
there's not human involvement and agency involved, and to what degree something
is הלכתית halachically considered a כלי kli or not, those things matter.
But presumably you needed an aqueduct off the ground and this עין
עיטם Ein Eitam had to start 23 אמה ama away—more than 23
אמה ama higher than the floor of the עזרה because it is
bringing it to the—because it's bringing it to the מקווה Mikva that's
on top of the שער המים, Sha'ar HaMayim, which is 23 אמות.
amot.
Does it matter like in terms of שאובין, she'uvin, the top of
the aqueduct where the water is flowing, it's not a closed pipe,
it's not closed? Did that make a difference?
Right, so that—yes, that could make a difference. But again, if it's
metal, it's still a בית קיבול beit kibul and whatever. So there's
a—yeah, so if it's clay, so that's—that's wonderful.
Okay, so it looks like it's stone.
Right, stone is fabulous. Stone isn't a כלי. kli. All right, so
God willing one of these days we'll learn מקואות, Mikva'ot, not really
because we're not doing דף יומי. Daf Yomi. I'll give you a
separate שיעור shiur in מקואות. Mikva'ot.
Rabbi, you're going to Israel.
All right, I'll come back and I'll report on the aqueduct. Okay,
very good. Let's go on. So it says like this. All right.
So the גמרא Gemara says, ואיכא אמה תקרה ואמה מעזיבה—one V'ika ama
tikra v'ama ma'aziva minute, says, you don't start building a מקווה Mikva
right on top of the top of the—of the gate, of the,
you know, you need first of all some thickness for the wall,
and then you need plaster before you're going to build something, especially
if the whole thing is supposed to be containing water. So there's
got to be—it's got to be higher than 23. So the גמרא
Gemara says, שערי דבית המקדש כיון דשישא נינהו—no, Sha'arei d'veit hamikdash kivan
d'shisha ninhu the gates of the בית המקדש, Beis HaMikdash, since they
were made out of marble. Now You need first of all some
thickness for the wall and then you need plaster before you're going
to build something, especially if the whole thing is supposed to be
containing water. So there's got to be, it's got to be higher
than twenty. So the גמרא Gemara says שערים דבית המקדש כיון דשיש
אינון. Sha'arin d'Beis HaMikdash keivan d'shaish inun. No, the gates of the
בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash. since they were made out of marble. Now,
I don't know, have they found marble gates? I mean, I assume
they're made out of stone, not marble. Have they ever found marble?
I know it's a stone, but have they found marble gates in
any of the excavations? Anyway, since they were made out of marble,
במשהו עבדי להו, b'mashu avdi lehu, you only need a small amount.
You know, marble is nice and strong and I think relatively non-porous,
is that correct? Yeah, so therefore you don't need a whole big
roof with plaster and the whole thing. You could start building, you
know, a thin roof and then you start building the מקוה mikveh
on top of it. So the גמרא Gemara says איי איכא היכא
משכחת לה, ai aika heicha mashkachat la, what about the little משהו
mashu that at least you need before you start building the מקוה?
mikveh כיון דלא הוי אמה לא חשיב ליה, keivan d'la havi amah
lo chashiv lei, it wasn't a full אמה, amah, לא חשיב ליה,
lo chashiv lei, we're rounding that, we're rounding to אמות, amos, so
it's twenty-three אמות amos and a little bit, so we round it
to twenty-three. Okay, that was an interesting little digression, but pointing out
an interesting question about how they get water to the
בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash.
Is this spring, this wellspring in the actual Temple court? That's something
else, right? Didn't they have like a spring that they used to
wash?
Yeah, but I think that that I have to I think that
that also fed all the water in the בית המקדש, not just
this.
Let's see. אמת המים Amas HaMayim from עיטם Eitam also?
I'd have to check. It would be very strange that they would
get their water from different sources. I mean, if you already have
a very good source and you're bothering to schlepp it all the
way to the בית המקדש.
That would make total sense because the aqueducts were relatively modern construction
and ירושלים Yerushalayim was ירושלים Yerushalayim and it became it was established
because it had a source of water.
So you're saying maybe they already had another water source in place
prior and they needed more water
and they took it
I'd have to look I'd I don't remember I'd have to look
into to see if that's explicit. Okay. פרסו סדין של בוץ. Parsu
sadin shel butz. Now before he actually went to the מקוה, mikveh
they spread out this linen garment, obviously to protect his privacy
since he's on a rooftop. So מאי שנא של בוץ, mai shna
shel butz, why linen? אמר רב כהנא כדי שיכיר שעבודת היום בבגדי
בוץ, amar Rav Kahana kedei sheyakir she’avodas hayom b’vigdei butz, so he
should remember that, you know, the special עבודת היום avodas hayom of
יום כיפור, Yom Kippur, half the עבודות avodos he's doing in the
בגדי זהב, bigdei zahav, normal gold garments, those are the weekday ones,
but the ones that are related to יום כיפור Yom Kippur and
that are more in the inner sanctum, those are in linen ones.
So you have this linen to remind him the special garments of
יום כיפור. Yom Kippur. הכא נמי כדי שיכיר שעבודת היום בבגדי בוץ.
hacha nami kedei sheyakir she’avodas hayom b’vigdei butz. So the same way
we're going to give that explanation why later when he changes his
clothes and does another one of the changings in the middle of
the day, they have a linen garment to protect his privacy. Here
too, same idea, they use linen garments because the special עבודות avodos
of the day are done with linen. Again, it's interesting the idea
that to remind him or he should he should not it doesn't
say to remind him, that he should acknowledge, that he should recognize.
You know, you might say because if we had to pick one
thing symbolically we're going to pick linen because that's what's special about
today is the linen garment. So maybe that's what it means here,
not like we're exactly afraid that he'll forget. תוספות Tosafos reads that
we're afraid he'll forget and put on the wrong garments, but it
could just mean, you know, to underscore the fact that this is
the special garments of the day. Okay, so now we're going to
get him actually going into the מקוה. mikveh... Let's take a look.
פשט ירד וטבל. Pashat yarad v'taval. So he stripped off his garments,
he went into the מקוה, Mikvah. he went he went he was
טובל, he immersed. עלה ונסתפג. Ala v'nistapeig.
He got up, he dried himself. הביאו לו בגדי זהב. Heviu lo
bigdei zahav. So they brought him now the gold garments because he
starts with the normal עבודות avodos of the day before the special
עבודות avodos of יום כיפור. Yom Kippur. ולבש. V'lavash. He put them
on. וקידש ידיו ורגליו V’kidesh yadav v’raglav וקידש וקידש וקידש. v’kidesh v’kidesh
v’kidesh. וקידש. V’kidesh. וקידש
ידיו ורגליו.
V’kidesh yadav
v’raglav. And he washed his hands and feet. Okay, so now we're
seeing, by the way, I told you that there were two washings
before and after the מקוה, Mikvah. so five מקוואות mikvaos become ten
washings, but if you notice here, it does not say you wash
before, it only says you wash after, because according to this approach,
the washing only was followed putting on בגדי קודש bigdei kodesh or
taking off בגדי קודש. bigdei kodesh. So you didn't have a washing
prior to the first one because before that, right, he was not
taking off בגדי קודש. bigdei kodesh. So then how are you going
to get ten? Because if you think about
it, okay, here's basically how it's going to work.
חול, Chol,
זהב, zahav,
בוץ, butz,
זהב, zahav, בוץ, butz, זהב, zahav, right? He's going to switch his
garments five times. Yes? Well, then בוץ butz and then back to
the weekday garments. Okay? So he's not going to have a washing
of the hands here, but he'll have it when he takes them
off here, that's one, right, puts them on two, takes them off
three, four, five, six, seven, eight, nine. Oh,
we're still stuck, aren't
we? One minute. Oh no no no, because here, here's what I
did
wrong, here's what I did wrong. Okay, so here he goes to
the מקוה. Mikvah, And that's what I did wrong. Right? He's going
to the מקווה mikvah between them, right? So that's five
times going to the מקווה. mikvah. וכל טבילה וטבילה, v'chol tvilah u-tvilah,
right? So here is the first time he washes his hands before
putting on the זהב. zahav.
Then he washes it
after taking it off, right?
Then before putting on, then...
So if you think about not just the
מקואות mikvaos before and after, but the clothes before and after, that's
how you're going to get ten, okay? The מקואות mikvaos are between
them, but the washing of the hands is before and after each
of the בגדים, bgadim, okay? So before the בגדי זהב, bigdei zahav,
and then when he takes it off, next time he goes to
take the מקווה, mikvah, he's going to take it off, wash his
hands, go to the מקווה, mikvah, wash his hands, put it on.
So it's before and after each one. Is he wearing the same
clothes? What? Same clothing or different? No, זהב לבן זהב לבן. zahav
lavan zahav lavan.
Okay, he's actually going to see, he actually wore different white garments
the second time than the first time. You have the change. Okay,
so let's take a look, okay?
הביאו לו בגדי זהב ולבש וקידש ידיו
ורגליו.
hevi'u lo bigdei zahav v'lavash
v'kidesh yadav v'raglav.
הביאו לו את התמיד. hevi'u lo et ha-tamid.
They brought him the קרבן
תמיד. korban tamid. סרצו, sirzo, he shechted it, which is a word
for shechting, the גמרא Gemara will explain that.
סרצו והביאו לו בגדי זהב ולבש וקידש ידיו
ורגליו.
sirzo v'hevi'u lo bigdei zahav v'lavash v'kidesh
yadav v'raglav.
Oh, I'm sorry, I already read that. והביאו לו בגדי זהב ולבש
וקידש ידיו ורגליו. v'hevi'u lo bigdei zahav v'lavash v'kidesh yadav v'raglav. I
read that.
Okay. Yeah, you put the first one right before the זהב, zahav,
here he did it after.
Fine. Right? No, what I meant was, this
is the time he's doing the עבודה avodah in the זהב. zahav.
Okay, here's
where he puts it on, and here's where he takes it off,
and here he's doing the עבודה, avodah, okay?
What was he taking off from the beginning, when it says...
His weekday clothes. That's why he's cold. His night clothes. Yeah. Okay,
so he washes his hands, he puts it on, he does the
עבודה, avodah, he takes it off, and he washes his hands. Okay?
הביאו לו בגדי זהב ולבש וקידש ידיו ורגליו. hevi'u lo bigdei zahav
v'lavash v'kidesh yadav v'raglav. הביאו לו את התמיד. hevi'u lo et ha-tamid.
They brought him the תמיד. tamid. סרצו, sirzo, he shechted it. ומרק
אחר שחיטה על ידו. u-mirek achar shechitah al yado. Another person finished
doing the שחיטה shechitah for him, like he wasn't...
the גמרא Gemara.
will discuss why it uses the word סרצו. sirzo. Anyway, he does
enough of the שחיטה רוב shechitah rov in order to be יוצא,
yotzei, and somebody else finishes the job. Again, he's in such a
rush, he can't even take... I never understood this, the extra half
a second to finish the job. Okay. It seems like it's just
so much more complicated and time-consuming to transfer it than to finish
it. That's
exactly the... to be מקבל m'kabel the דם. dam. I understand, but
keep... we're going to say that, but yeah. Okay. Yeah, I guess
it's true, it's not just that he's in a rush, it's that
he has to quickly change in order to get the דם. dam.
Yeah, you're right, he has to switch over, so it's not just
the time issue. It's not the time, like, big picture, it's just
to immediately shift to be מקבל m'kabel the דם, dam, yeah. I
still don't exactly get it. I mean, you have to be sort
of holding the thing here, but you can't, by the way, שוחט
shochet with one and hold with another because you have to do
עבודה avodah in the right hand. So in the way, some blood
is going to escape. Again, maybe if you just did רוב, rov,
the blood doesn't start squirting out right away and that gives you
the time to catch it, but you know, then it would only
start squirting out a second later when you finish the שחיטה. shechitah.
Yes.
How can you do a שחיטה shechitah where you start and then
stop and then keep going? Is that still כשר? kosher?
Yeah, well, you mean about the issue about שהייה. shehiyah. Yeah, but
no, but if you did רוב rov and you were יוצא yotzei
already, then it's okay. Now there is actual... you were יוצא, yotzei,
so anything else is like you could chop off the head of
the animal now. You don't have to do a שחיטה, shechitah, okay?
There is an interesting רש''י Rashi that talks about if you do
a פסול psul after רוב rov and finish it, does maybe the
finishing make it פסול pasul because the פסול psul now got integrated
into it. But anyway...
And then the animal is tortured, it's still alive, it's like half
dead.
That's every animal that you שוחט, shochet, every time...
But you go, you don't stop.
You mean the fact that we pause makes it more... it causes
more pain. Oh yeah. Yeah, I don't know, I assume that's true,
I don't have an answer to that. I don't have an answer
to that. There, you shechted רוב.
rov. What? Does it die right there when you shecht
רוב rov at that point? Yeah, so it's יוצא. yotzei. It's over.
It's over for the שחיטה, shechitah, but Rivka is saying that there's
still suffering if you do it more. Of course.
It's not clear that...
while you're
bleeding out at
that point when it's over, like... Right, right, it's actually dying...
Right, they care, everybody cares... No, I think it's a modern... Okay,
okay, I'm going to keep on reading now.
Okay, קיבל את הדם.
kibel
et ha-dam.
So then he went, because,
as Jonathan correctly said, he, you know, had to finish quickly, he
couldn't do the whole thing because he had to quickly transfer to
get... to be מקבל m'kabel the דם. dam. וזרקו, v'zarko, he threw
the דם, dam, because we had already spoken about how this whole
process about bringing the תמיד, tamid, so now we have that background,
now we're going to see how the כהן גדול Kohen Gadol. is
going to do it, and it's not going to be this thing
that's divided amongst all these כהנים. kohanim. נכנס להקטיר קטורת של שחר,
nichnas l'haktir ktoret shel shachar, then after the דם dam of the
תמיד, tamid, he did the... he went to burn the morning incense.
ולהטיב את הנרות ul'heitiv et hanerot to clean out the נרות. nerot.
And then he went—and what of the two and the five? Alright,
but that was all discussed before. ולהקריב את הראש, ul'hakriv et harosh,
now we're getting to talk about the limbs to the ram. You
see how good it is that we had those earlier משניות? mishnayot?
Now
you know exactly what it's talking about. ולהקריב את הראש ואת האיברים,
ul'hakriv et harosh v'et ha'evarim, the head and the other limbs, you
put it on the ramp. והחביתין, ve'hachavitin, and remember there were other
things that were brought with the limbs. For example, the חביתין, chavitin,
which is the מנחה mincha of the כהן גדול, Kohen Gadol which
he would bring half in the morning and half in the afternoon.
ויין, v'hayayin, and the wine that came with it, the מנחת נסכים.
minchat nesachim. קטורת של שחר הייתה קריבה בין דם לאיברים. ketoret shel
shachar hayta kreiva bein dam le'evarim. Now we're going to talk again
about a general rule. The morning קטורת ketoret was burnt out between
the throwing of the דם dam of the תמיד tamid and the
limbs, as this משנה mishna said: he threw the דם dam and
then he did the קטורת. ketoret. של בין הערביים, shel bein ha'arbayim,
the afternoon קטורת, ketoret, בין איברים לנסכים. bein evarim lanesachim. That what
they would do after the limbs of the afternoon תמיד tamid were
brought up, not after the דם; dam; they did the דם, dam,
then the limbs, and then they did the קטורת, ketoret, and then
they did the נסכים, nesachim, the wine and the flour. Okay. אם
היה כהן גדול זקן או אסטניס, im haya kohein gadol zaken o
istinis, if the כהן Kohen גדול was elderly or he was very
fastidious, okay, and now we're not—and you think you're talking about something
relating to the עבודה, avoda, but now we're doubling back to talk
about the מקוה, Mikvah, again, funny that we're doubling back to talk
about the מקוה Mikvah. now. מחממין לו חמין ומטילין לתוך הצונן. mechammemin
lo chammin umatilin letoch hatzonen. You would heat up hot water and
put it into the cold water כדי שתפיג צינתן, keday shetafig tzinatan,
so not be—so in order to sort of, you know, absorb the
cold, yeah, in order to right, in order to—in order to warm—to
remove some of its coldness, some of the cold. Okay, which is
going to lead to interesting questions about בישול bishul questions on שבת
Shabbat and—and יום כיפור, Yom Kippur, right? Can you put hot water
in cold water? Aren't you heating up the cold water? What about
בישול? bishul? So we'll take a look at that when we get
to the גמרא. Gemara So that's a good question too, right?
What—if they had a fire going somewhere, and how did they—now, how
is it not פסול המקוה? pasul hamikveh? That's not a problem, because
once you have a כשר מקוה kosher mikveh of ארבעים סאה, arbayim
se'ah, you can put in a lot of drawn water and it
doesn't invalidate it. That's why for example our מקואות, mikvaot, there's the
בור bor of the מי גשמים mei geshamim that has the כשר
מקוה
kosher mikveh of the ארבעים סאה, arbayim se'ah, and then it's connected
through a tiny little hole, and then the מקוה Mikvah that actually
is used is fresh water that's put in and changed on a
regular basis.
Because right, because once you have a כשר מקוה, kosher mikveh, you
can add
as much as you want to it and you don't invalidate it.
So it's not a problem that they're heating up water for, you
know, and it's drawn water and then they're bringing it. The question
is how you're doing this on יום טוב, Yom Tov, is that
how you're doing it on יום כיפור? Yom Kippur? Okay, so we'll
take a look. Okay, but they did it כדי שתפיג צינתן keday
shetafig tzinatan to remove the cold. Okay. אמרו רבנן קמיה דרב פפא.
amru rabanan kamei deRav Pappa. So the rabbis said, the rabbis, the
rabbinic students, said to רב פפא, Rav Pappa, הא דלא כרבי מאיר,
ha d'lo k'Rabbi Meir, this is not like רבי מאיר. Rabbi Meir.
דאי כרבי מאיר, d'ei k'Rabbi Meir, according to רבי מאיר, Rabbi Meir,
we'll see which רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir we're talking about, okay. So
כיון דאמר תרי קידושי אלבישה עבדי להו, keivan d'amar terei kiddushei alvishah
avdi lehu, הכא נמי לבעי תרי קידושי אלבישה. hacha nami liv'ei terei
kiddushei alvishah. Because according to רבי מאיר, Rabbi Meir, you—we'll see later,
it's not like—it's not here, but you did it, you did it,
and then you put it on, and then you took it off.
If you want us to be even more precise, okay, you did
a קידוש kiddush and then you put it on, then you took
it off and then you did the קידוש. kiddush. Right, that's how
we have it: before putting it on and then after taking it
off. But רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir says you do the two of
them before and—and after. You put it before taking it off and
after putting it on. Okay, so according to him, right, הא משנה
ha mishna is not like רבי מאיר, Rabbi Meir, because our משנה
mishna should have mentioned, right, two טבילות—so tvilot let's take a look—two
קידושי ידיים, kiddushei yadayim, right. One minute. Right. Okay. So the גמרא
Gemara says like this, דאי כרבי מאיר, d'ei k'Rabbi Meir, if it's
like רבי מאיר, Rabbi Meir, כיון דאמר תרי קידושי אלבישה עבדי להו,
keivan d'amar terei kiddushei alvishah avdi lehu, since he says you do
the two washings when you put it on, הכא נמי לבעי תרי
קידושי אלבישה. hacha nami liv'ei terei kiddushei alvishah. So our משנה mishna
should have said that. So our משנה mishna is not like רבי
מאיר. Rabbi Meir. Our משנה mishna has it between about putting on
and taking off, it does not have it about—it does not have
it about before and after. Actually, I think I did it wrong.
I think I did it wrong. Our משנה mishna has it—I did
it wrong, I'm sorry, I apologize. Our משנה mishna has it you
put it on and then you do the לבישה, levisha, okay, and
then you take it off and you do it. So our משנה
mishna actually we have it after putting it on and after taking
it off. But רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir says it's supposed to be
relating to the לבישה levisha and that therefore our משנה mishna is
clearly not like רבי מאיר. Rabbi Meir. Okay, so is that clear?
Have I managed to confuse everybody? You did one big one instead
of four. I'm sorry, I'm sorry, I think I've successfully managed to
confuse everybody. Okay, so here's your חול chol garment, okay, here is
your—your—your קודש kodesh garments, your זהב. zahav. Okay, here's where you put
it on. You put it on
and here's where you take it off. Our משנה mishna said that
you wash your hands—you go to the מקוה Mikvah and you have
a מקוה Mikvah, here too. Out between this and the זהב. zahav.
You go to the מקוה... Mikvah You put it on and then
you wash, okay. That's our משנה Mishnah's approach. Go to the מקווה,
Mikvah, put on your new clothes and then do a wash. Okay,
yes to here? And that's why if you have these five times,
it's going to become ten. Okay, רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir says wait
a minute, רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir says no. What רבי מאיר Rabbi
Meir says is that you do it before you put it on
and after you put it on.
Okay, that's רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir says.
It's not about taking off, so according to רבי מאיר, Rabbi Meir,
you would not do number two here, you did number two there.
And then here where we have the לבן, Lavan, right, when we
have the same thing, the on and the off, right, רבי מאיר
Rabbi Meir would say that this would be three and this would
be four. Okay, it's before and after putting on. So רבי מאיר
Rabbi Meir you get two for each change of clothes, but it's
all related to the putting on, the before and the after.
The taking off is just the taking off.
Right, that is רבי מאיר. Rabbi Meir.
Well, you have to take them off before you can put them
on. Do we still have ten?
Well, yes, we still have ten because you have two associated with
each clothes. Okay, but according to the רבנן, Rabbanan no, it is
one after putting on and it is one after taking off. Okay,
so that is the debate. Is it after you go on and
after you go off, or before and after you put it on?
Is wearing these clothing an עבודה? Avodah?
The after wearing the clothing an עבודה... Avodah...
no,
yeah, but I it's an interesting way of framing it. Let's see
when we get to that. I don't think that that's I'm not
maybe. Maybe that that's somewhat of what it's based on, but I
wouldn't commit to that yet. Okay, so let's take a look at
what the גמרא Gemara says like this. Okay. So,
דרבי מאיר כיון דאמר תרי קידושי אליבישה, De-Rabbi Meir, keivan de-amar trei
kiddushei a-levishah, רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir says you wash your hands twice
when you get when you put on the clothes, before and after
you put them on. אי הכי הכא נמי להוו תרי קידושי? Ei
hachi hacha nami lihavu trei kiddushei? It should have said you did
it twice, before and after you put them on, and ours only
said you did it after you put it on. אמר ליה רב
פפא לאביי, Amar leh Rav Pappa le-Abaye, so רב פפא Rav Pappa
says, בין רבנן בין רבי מאיר, bein Rabbanan bein Rabbi Meir, חד
אפשיטה דבגדי קודש וחד אלבישה. chad a-pshitah de-vigdei kodesh ve-chad a-levishah. Both
the Rabbis and רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir agree that it is that
one of the washing hands is for when you're taking off the
holy garments, meaning it's not for בגדי חול, bigdei chol, and one
for putting on the garments. והכא בהא קמפלגי. Ve-hacha be-ha kam miflegi.
So here's the debate: ופשט ורחץ ולבש, U-fashat ve-rachatz ve-lavash, right, that's
what the פסוק pasuk? says. ופשט בגדיו ורחץ את בשרו במים ולבש
בגדיו... U-fashat begadav ve-rachatz et besaro ba-mayim ve-lavash begadav... you know, where's
the whole פסוק?
ופשט את בגדיו ולבש בגדים אחרים... U-fashat et begadav ve-lavash begadim acherim...
והוציא את הדשן...
ve-hotzi et hadeshen... מחוץ למחנה... achutz lamachaneh... something, something, something...
אל מקום טהור... el mekom tahor... והוציא את הדשן... ve-hotzi et hadeshen...
yeah,
that's no, but that's by צו, Tzav, that's a different ופשט. u-fashat.
That's not by כהן גדול.
That's not by יום כיפור. Yom Kippur.
You have it?
Yes, I've got it all in here somewhere.
What is it? Go ahead, say it.
Okay,
let's take a look.
Sefaria really did not do this right. They should have said where
else
in the גמרא Gemara this
comes up.
Yeah, that would help.
Oh,
do you have it in your דף יומי Daf Yomi thing? Does
it say?
In the Artscroll, actually, it has it. Oh, yeah, it's in the
Artscroll.
ופשט את בגדי הקודש... U-fashat et bigdei hakodesh...
no,
that's a different one, hold on. ופשט את בגדי הבד אשר לבש
בבאו אל הקודש והניחם שם. U-fashat et bigdei habad asher lavash be-vo'o
el hakodesh ve-hini-cham sham. That's the one I was that's what I
was reading. ופשט את בגדי הבד אשר... oh, yes, thank you. ופשט
את בגדי הבד אשר לבש בבאו אל הקודש והניחם שם ורחץ את
בשרו במים במקום קדוש ולבש את בגדיו. ve-lavash et begadav, So then
you take it off, you then רחץ, rachatz, and then ולבש את
בגדיו, begadav okay, and the בגדיו is the is the
בגדי קודש. bigdei kodesh. ופשט רחץ ולבש. U-fashat, rachatz, ve-lavash. רבי מאיר
סבר, Rabbi Meir savar, רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir holds, מקיש פשיטה ללבישה.
makish pshitah le-levishah. You connect the taking off to the putting on.
מה לבישה לביש ואחר כך מקדש, Mah levishah lavish ve-acharkach mekadesh, the
same way when you put on, you put on and then wash
your hands (how we know that is not clear yet, but we'll
take that for granted), אף פשיטה, af pshitah, even when you take
them off, פושט ואחר כך מקדש. poshet ve-acharkach mekadesh. You take it
off and then you wash your hands. You wash it after you
take it off. ורבנן סברי, Ve-Rabbanan savri, and the Rabbis hold, מקיש
פשיטה ללבישה. makish pshitah le-levishah.
No, here's the connection: מה לבישה כשהוא לבוש מקדש, mah levishah keshehu
lavush mekadesh,
the same way when by פשיטה pshitah when he is dressed he
washes his hands, אף פשיטה כשהוא לבוש מקדש. af pshitah keshehu lavush
mekadesh.
Even when he takes it off, he takes it off when he
is dressed. What when he still even when he washes it in
the process of taking it off, it's while he is still dressed.
What does this mean?
It means that we had said that the debate of the רבנן
Rabbanan and רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir is that the רבנן Rabbanan would
be saying
after putting on and after taking off, okay,
and רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir would say that you did it, right,
before and after putting on. Okay, but that it was all related
to the בגדי זהב. Bigdei Zahav. Okay? We thought that it was
all related not to what you took off but to what you're
putting on. And that רבי מאיר Rebbi Meir was just saying before
and after the thing you put on. And therefore in our משנה
Mishnah he should have had two, not just one. That was our
question, right? But why what makes us say that according to רבי
מאיר? Rebbi Meir? What makes us say that according to רבי מאיר
Rebbi Meir is because רבי מאיר, Rebbi Meir, when we're going to
talk in another משנה Mishnah about switching from the gold to the
white, רבי מאיר Rebbi Meir is going to say you do one
here, right, and one here. So we're saying, ah, according to רבי
מאיר Rebbi Meir look, it's not before and after putting it on,
right, because it's one here and one here, and therefore it should
have here been two as well in our משנה. Mishnah. But comes
along רב פפא Rav Papa and רב פפא Rav Papa says you
got it all wrong. Right? There's another way to interpret the before
and after here putting it on. What's the other way to interpret
the before and after?
After going to the...
This isn't about before putting on the clothes, it's about after taking
off the gold clothes. And therefore the reason even רבי מאיר Rebbi
Meir would say you don't have it here, right, because there's חול
chol clothes. So really, you've got the debate wrong, okay? The point
is like this: רבי מאיר Rebbi Meir holds that the whole debate
is everybody agrees it is not about taking it is not about
two washings for the new clothes. Everybody agrees it relates to the
old clothes. So you're not going to do it here. The whole
debate is when do you do this washing? רבי מאיר Rebbi Meir
says you do this washing after you go to the מקוה. Mikvah,
Okay, yes, it's about the old clothes, but you do it after
you go to the מקוה. Mikvah Seems a little funny that it's
about the old clothes, but nevertheless, that's what he says. רבנן Rabbanan,
say no, you don't do the washing after you go to the
מקוה, Mikvah.
the washing that you're going to do is going to be before
before you even take
off before you even take off your old clothes. Now what's the
difference? What's the reason? So let's take a look. So the גמרא
Gemara says like this, let's read it again. רבי מאיר סבר מקיש
פשיטה ללבישה. Rebbi Meir savor makish peshitah lilevishah.
You connect the taking off to the putting on. מה לבישה לובש
אחר מקדש, Mah levishah lovesh achar kadesh,
the same way when you put it on, first you take it
off and then you wash your hands, אף פשיטה פושט ואחר מקדש.
af peshitah poshet ve'achar mikadesh.
Okay, so the same way here, what happens here?
You put on your clothes
and then you do the washing of the hands. So similarly when
it comes here, says רבי מאיר, Rebbi Meir, you're first going to
take off your clothes and then you're going to do the washing
of your hands. Okay now why it's after you go to the
מקוה, Mikvah. we'll talk about, but anyway that's what he says. That's
why he says it comes here because you take off your clothes...
you add them at least put that before the מקוה. Mikvah. I
know. Because he's not talking about when the מקוה Mikvah. is. I'm
making it more confusing. But okay. Okay, so anyway, okay, so he
says רבי מאיר Rebbi Meir says, I say the same way you
put on your clothes and you wash your hands, you take off
your clothes and you wash your hands. So therefore it could be
confusing which it's going on, but it's really going here on the
taking off of the clothes. Okay, I just say that you the
same way you put it on, you you put on and you
wash your hands, you take off and wash your hands. What do
the Rabbis say? Wait one minute, wait just let me just finish
this. Okay, רבנן סברי Rabbanan savori and the Rabbis say מקיש פשיטה
ללבישה, makish peshitah lilevishah, מה לבישה כשהוא לבוש מקדש, mah levishah keshelavush
mekadesh, אף פשיטה כשהוא לבוש מקדש. af peshitah keshelavush mekadesh.
The Rabbis say no, because you go the same way
here you're dressed when you wash your hands, when you're doing it
for what you take off we still want you to be dressed
while you're washing your hands. We don't want you to be do
it when you're undressed. Okay, so at the end of the day
they both agree that this is relates to the garments you take
off, and therefore nobody has one here when you switch from בגדי
חול. bigdei chol. The question is if it's about the garment you
take off, do you do it before you take them off so
that you'll still be dressed the same way you're dressed here, or
do you do it after the act of taking it off the
same way this comes after the act of
putting it on.
Okay, but when רבי מאיר Rebbi Meir says before and after
here, it's not because it relates to putting it on, it relates
to taking off. Okay, we heard nothing when he's going to switch...
according to רבי מאיר Rebbi Meir
yes, wearing nothing.
Right, according to רבי מאיר, Rebbi Meir, yes.
It violates the question which should have been obvious before I guess,
but I would think the מקוה Mikvah, is like supersede.
Right, right, right.
But no, I mean look, there's a הלכה that a כהן גדול
a כהן cannot be נכנס nechnas to what do you call it,
you know, without קידוש ידים ורגלים. kiddush yadayim veraglayim. And even if
he's gone to the מקוה, Mikvah, right, the the תורה says that
he has to קידוש ידים ורגלים kiddush yadayim veraglayim or else you
know he's חייב מיתה. So that's a specific act of קידוש ידים
ורגלים. kiddush yadayim veraglayim. You're right, in terms of like טומאה וטהרה,
מקוה Mikvah, supersedes. But in terms of like this ritual, then there's
something special to the distinct to the קידוש ידים ורגלים. kiddush yadayim
veraglayim. You're totally right.
Did he do it himself?
Does somebody pour the
water on his hands
and legs?
Yeah.
Somebody? No, he does it.
He he puts his hands on
his legs and he
right, puts his hands in the water.
No, step... No, he holds his he holds a hand... What? Everybody
had to wash the feet before you went into the
בית
המקדש.
Yes.
Okay, but here he's doing it every time before he goes. Here
he's doing— but here he's doing it every time he switches. Okay,
I just double-checked. I'm sorry, I think I'm confusing people today. But
what— but I just double-checked, and yes, according to רבי מאיר, Rabbi
Meir, this is before he goes to the מקוה, Mikvah. which actually
accords with רב פפא's Rav Pappa's explanation. Okay, the later משנה Mishnah
says if you take a look at ל"ד ע"ב, Lamed Daled Amud
Bais, that's the רבי מאיר. Rabbi Meir. Let's look at that quickly.
Okay, it says, הביאו לו בית הפרוה ובקודש הייתה פירסו סדין של
בוץ בינו לבין העם וקידש ידיו ורגליו ופשט. Hevi'u lo beis haparvah
uvakodesh hayetah pirsu sadin shel butz beino uvein ha'am vekiddesh yadav v'raglav
uphasht. רבי מאיר אומר פשט וקידש ידיו ורגליו, Rabbi Meir omer phasht
vekiddesh yadav v'raglav, and
then ירד וטבל. Yarad v'taval.
Okay?
So it's very clear here that the מקוה Mikvah going is— everybody
agrees that the קידוש Kiddush comes before the מקוה. Mikvah. The only
question here is the debate about רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir and the
רבנן, Rabbanan is it before or after you take off your clothes?
Okay, the רבנן Rabbanan say it's before you take off your clothes
and רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir says it's after you take off your
clothes, but everybody agrees that it's before the מקוה. Mikvah. So I'm
sorry, I think I was confusing people before. So now you understand
what רב פפא Rav Pappa is saying? He's saying רבי מאיר Rabbi
Meir isn't doing it about dressing the new clothes. He's having you
do it before you go to the מקוה. mikvah, It's all about
taking off your old clothes. The only question is before you take
off your old clothes or after you take off your old clothes.
But it's all about the old clothes, and therefore everybody agrees you
don't get one here because these are your weekday clothes. But when
they're קודש Kodesh clothes, the whole debate is before or after you
take off the clothes. Okay, so let's see now what the רבנן
Rabbanan, say.
So אמרו ליה רבנן לרב פפא, Amru lei Rabbanan leRav Pappa, so
the rabbis said back to רב פפא. Rav Pappa. Remember the rabbis
here, the rabbinic students felt that according to רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir
it was about the new clothes, not about the old clothes. ומי
מצית אמרת הכי, Umi matzis amart hachi, how can you say that?
דתניא, Detanya, it's taught in a ברייתא, Baraisa, פירסו סדין של בוץ
בינו לבין העם, Pirsu sadin shel butz beino uvein ha'am, they spread
out this linen garment.
פשט וירד וטבל, Phasht veyarad v'taval, he took off his clothes and
he went down to a מקוה. mikvah, עלה ונסתפג, Ala venistapeig, he
dried off. הביאו לו בגדי זהב, Hevi'u lo bigdei zahav, they brought
him the gold clothes. ולבש וקידש ידיו ורגליו, Velavash vekiddesh yadav v'raglav,
and he washed his hands. So that's like we understand. Go to
the מקוה, mikvah, get dressed, wash your hands. רבי מאיר אומר פשט,
Rabbi Meir omer phasht, took off your old clothes, וקידש ידיו ורגליו,
vekiddesh yadav v'raglav, go to the מקוה, mikvah I mean do the—
do the נטילה. Netilah. וירד וטבל, Veyarad v'taval, go down. עלה ונסתפג
הביאו לו בגדי זהב ולבש וקידש ידיו ורגליו. Ala venistapeig hevi'u lo
bigdei zahav velavash vekiddesh yadav v'raglav. So meaning we have a ברייתא
Baraisa which explicitly is understood again, not exactly clear how you know
this ברייתא Baraisa is talking about— about the first change. But he
says we actually have a ברייתא Baraisa that says that according to
רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir that you would actually go— that it says
that when you're switching from בגדי חול bigdei chol that according to
רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir you would wash your hands. Right, what does
the ברייתא Baraisa say? It says he's going to בגדי זהב. bigdei
zahav. One minute. בינו לבין העם פשט וירד וטבל עלה ונסתפג הביאו
לו בגדי זהב ולבש רבי מאיר אומר פשט וקידש ידיו ורגליו וירד
וטבל. Beino uvein ha'am phasht veyarad v'taval ala venistapeig hevi'u lo bigdei
zahav velavash Rabbi Meir omer phasht vekiddesh yadav v'raglav veyarad v'taval.
We have a ברייתא Baraisa that explicitly says that this— that the
same debate here happens here, right?
According to the רבנן, Rabbanan according to רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir you
would do number one and number two before and after the מקוה,
and according to the רבנן Rabbanan, you would only do it after
the מקוה.
Because the point is— so that's the point.
The גמרא Gemara somehow the— understood that the context is the first
washing. So the same way here there's a debate, right, whether you
did it before going to the מקוה or not, here too we
have a debate where רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir says that you actually
wash your hands before going to the מקוה. And they understand that
that means that's the first time you are changing clothes. Okay, so
does everybody see that? If we assume it's the first time you're
changing clothes, he says look, here the רבנן, Rabbanan here's רבי מאיר
Rabbi Meir is saying it. Let's read רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir again.
Okay, רבי מאיר אומר, Rabbi Meir omer, it's again, it's not obvious
that we're talking about the first change of clothes, but that's the
context they understand. רבי מאיר אומר פשט, Rabbi Meir omer phasht, take
off, understood to be your weekday clothes, וקידש ידיו ורגליו, vekiddesh yadav
v'raglav, and wash your hands. וירד וטבל, Veyarad v'taval, go to the
מקוה. עלה ונסתפג הביאו לו בגדי זהב ולבש וקידש ידיו ורגליו. Ala
venistapeig hevi'u lo bigdei zahav velavash vekiddesh yadav v'raglav. So he says
look, I've got a ברייתא Baraisa that says that you would wash
your hands for רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir even when you take off
your weekday clothes. So the גמרא says אמרו ליה אי תניא תניא.
Amru lei ei tanya tanya. Okay, if you've got a ברייתא Baraisa
so what can I do? Okay, but it's not exactly clear that
it means that he agrees. So basically again, I know this is
getting confusing, okay, let's try, but I want to try to repeat
it one last time, okay. So here you have
weekday clothes and your קודש Kodesh clothes. Okay, and we'll start with
this again, your קודש Kodesh clothes. So רבי מאיר, Rabbi Meir, let's
focus on רבי מאיר, Rabbi Meir, what רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir says.
רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir says, according to רבי מאיר, Rabbi Meir, you—
you do wash number one and then wash number— What? Let's just,
this is all preparatory to
your בגדי קודש. bigdei kodesh. You wash, you go to the מקוה,
you put it on, you wash, and all of that relates to
your בגדי קודש. bigdei kodesh. If that were true, then you would
do it even in this first transition as well. That's what the
Rabbis want to say. And why isn't רבי מאיר Rebbe Meir doing
it? It must be our משנה Mishna is not רבי מאיר. Rebbe
Meir. רב פפא Rav Pappa says a much more reasonable thing. He
says this is not, the first one isn't related to your בגדי
קודש. bigdei kodesh. The first one is related to your בגדי חול.
bigdei chol. Okay? And that's what the first one is about. So
the only debate of רבי מאיר Rebbe Meir and the רבנן Rabbanan
is that רבי מאיר Rebbe Meir says first take off your clothes
then you do it and the רבנן Rabbanan, say, so this is
רבי מאיר Rebbe Meir and this is the רבנן, Rabbanan they say
you do while your clothes are still on. But everybody agrees it
relates to the clothes you're taking off and therefore you're not going
to do it here according to רבי מאיר. Rebbe Meir. Okay. So
basically everybody agrees wash your hands, go to
the מקוה, wash your hands. The whole debate of רבי מאיר Rebbe
Meir and the רבנן is do you do the washing of the
first time after you've taken off your clothes or before you've taken
off your clothes? And that leads to a conceptual debate of is
רבי מאיר Rebbe Meir about preparing for the בגדי קודש? bigdei kodesh?
Is that one way of understanding רבי מאיר? Rebbe Meir? Or is
it just about taking off the clothes but just you do it
after? And the נפקא מינא nafka mina is the בגדי חול. bigdei
chol. If it's about preparing for the בגדי קודש, bigdei kodesh, so
then רבי מאיר Rebbe Meir would say the same way. רבי מאיר
Rebbe Meir would say if it's about preparing
for the בגדי קודש, bigdei kodesh, so
the preparing consists of
three things: one washing of a hand, one מקוה, and another washing
of a hand.
That's what רבי מאיר Rebbe Meir would say. If it's about getting
off of the בגדי חול, bigdei chol, then he would not, then
it would not start, then you would not have that first washing.
Okay, so that is the question about whether רבי מאיר Rebbe Meir
would say you do one washing before you go to the מקוה
and they have a ברייתא braita that supports it, but רב פפא
Rav Pappa is very reasonably saying I don't think according to רבי
מאיר Rebbe Meir it's about preparing for the new clothes, I think
the first washing is for taking off the old clothes and even
רבי מאיר Rebbe Meir would agree you would not have it when
you do that first transition. Okay, we'll end here, I think I
successfully...
What? תניא תניא. tanya tanya.